Software Engineering Radio episode 27
service oriented architecture part one.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
This is the first episode in our mini
series on service oriented
architectures.
In this episode myself Marcus and
Eberhard
will be talking about
the basics of service oriented
architectures motivating the topic and
coming up with a relatively
non-technical view on SOA in subsequent
episodes or subsequent parts of this SOA
series will get more and more technical
and more and more specific.
And we will also talk about the the
historic origins of SOA.
Right.
As you said we should probably start by
motivating where SOA comes from from
which other
philosophies or or or
paradigms it developed and
I think you you've prepared a prepared a
little case study from which we can
start right?
Yeah, it's an imaginary case study. So
what we do is
we
have a company and we look at how the
company developed its software
environment and its IT infrastructure
during the several different
technologies
and the case that we are going to talk
about is how they deal with the orders
that come in because this is something
that every company does and it also has
interfaces to all of the other processes
that are there in
the in the company.
So, in the beginning,
um which is in our case about the '70s,
There was light.
Yeah, sort of. In the beginning, there
was the word, I think. And
Anyway,
uh so,
uh in the '70s, um the the company
started doing IT stuff. Um and in our
case, as usual, with uh mainframes. And
to get historic comparison, uh in 1972,
the German company SAP was founded. So,
this is where
in those times, it was mostly
handwritten software that was used. So,
they developed a monolithic um
mainframe application with terminals.
And a
a batch-oriented system. So, all the
orders of the day are processed in one
big batch. And this is sort of um the
the first step of the IT system in um
yeah, in the company.
The next technology that we are that
evolved were PCs in the '80s,
um because of things like uh spreadsheet
applications, uh and uh shrink-wrapped
uh office applications.
And also terminal emulations were used
on those PCs to get access to the
mainframe. And also new servers showed
up that were used uh by the several
parts of the company to store their own
files in. And this was in the '90s, uh
the PCs were
um
uh graphical user interfaces were added
to the PCs in the '90s. And now the
question arises whether this should be
used for the
uh applications of the company itself
also, and not just for the
shrink-wrapped applications that they
buy from some vendors.
So, you're saying that the real
applications of the enterprise were
still server or mainframe based with
terminal emulations and the GUIs on the
clients were only used for those ad hoc,
uh you know, Excel or Multiplan or
whatever it was called, uh spreadsheet
calculations.
VisiCalc and things like that.
Right. Exactly. And then a graphical
user interfaces came up with X for
example and now the question is uh
can't we have something more nice if for
the for those
um
individual applications as well.
And that's probably where client-server
compute computing came up then.
And also to certain degree object
orientation, I think.
Okay.
Uh so, in in my opinion, object
orientation is uh somehow connected to
graphical user interfaces to a certain
extent because it's uh quite nice and
easy to do
uh graphic user interfaces using
object-oriented systems.
And uh you can see this by
that that
Smalltalk, for example, was closely
linked to graphic user interfaces. Uh
things like Microsoft Foundation
Classes, also if you look at the
original design patterns, a lot of the
things were about graphic user
interfaces. Uh
the examples in this book were about
graphic user interfaces. So, it's
somehow linked. It's not
And that's
There was this this this framework where
Erich Gamma worked on, I forget how it's
called, but many of the examples in the
GoF book are from that framework.
Exactly.
So,
um
So, why using object orientation?
Because of graphic user interfaces, as I
said, and nowadays it's
becoming more important that it's an
integrated uh development model. So, you
have a means to analyze uh the business
for design and also for programming.
And the big
things that were promised were uh better
maintainability,
better reuse, and things like that.
And as we all know, this only
materialized to some extent.
To a certain extent.
Yeah.
Exactly, yeah.
And uh now if you look at the the
structure of uh the the IT system that
we have
in this company, we have this monolithic
uh mainframe application. And if you do
some kind of uh graphical user interface
uh
thing for order processing, the problem
is that the mainframe application is
still there, and you still have to deal
with it.
So, what usually happens is that you
actually do a rather
thin application in some object-oriented
language like C++ for example, and the
real business logic is still on the
mainframe.
So, this is what what the company
learned during this project. Yes, you
can do a GUI with this object-oriented
system.
Uh object-oriented
analysis and design are probably not as
natural as uh one would think. So, the
the things that were there at the um
the ideas, like for example,
um
that you just write down a text about
the case, and then you underline certain
words, and this is more or less your
design. This is obviously quite naive.
Yeah.
And uh also as we mentioned, reuse is
not as easy. But the main problem coming
from the general IT perspective is that
the object-oriented technology is not
really doing
um
it's not really cannot be used uh
throughout the company, because the
mainframe is not object-oriented.
The database
uh
is often a relational database, and also
batch applications, for example, that
have on the mainframe are not covered at
all.
So, you say that the OO model was only
useful for this relatively unimportant
part compared to the rest of graphical
user interfaces, and the real stuff
wasn't wasn't migrated or wasn't
touched.
Exactly.
And um so, what the people came up with
is uh that
uh the problems that arises that logical
is is done redundant in the client front
and in in the mainframe as well.
And um
there is also no clear concept of
foreign migration. So, if you just say,
"Okay, we going we are going to take all
the logic from the mainframe to the
front end." This usually didn't happen.
And uh also, in terms of reliability and
throughput and so on, it's just
something that you can't do with
technologies like uh C++ and Windows by
that time. So, we are talking about the
'90s here.
Yeah. Yeah, there were several mainframe
migration projects, but the goal was to
switch off the mainframe and do
everything on on classes of PCs with
client server, but
I know several projects that didn't that
failed.
Yeah.
Um actually, what you're talking about
is sort of the next step.
Ah.
Um so,
instead of having just normal PCs on
every desk, uh you do um what what you
need is some kind of modernized server
infrastructure. And this is where this
uh
clustering comes in and where you have
to use
clusters of of servers.
But this is not this is more related to
component um software engineering.
So, you are separating the system into
several components, and you're using
technologies such as CORBA,
uh COM DCOM or
the Microsoft side, or the famous J2EE
on the Java side, uh to have an
environment in which you can have sort
of enterprise objects that are more
reliable, more scalable, uh and are
therefore more close to what the
mainframe can actually do.
Mhm.
Yeah, and um the reason for that was, of
course, easier reuse, um
to separate technical concerns from
uh the business logic. And I think again
it was related to a shift a technology
shift. So, instead of having graphical
user interfaces, now web interfaces came
up. And this is a new thing that you
have to think about.
But what's the relationship between web
interfaces and uh component-based
software without the mainframe, except
that they happened at the same time? But
there wasn't any causal connection, was
there?
One of the reasons
uh that were stated for using
component-oriented software is that you
have to centralize your business logic
on a server to reuse it from what we
call now rich clients and web interfaces
as well.
Okay, so you're saying since since the
business logic was on the centralized
machines anyway, you could easily have
very thin clients, and that would be the
web clients.
Yeah, or rather the other way around,
because you want to have access to the
business logic from web clients as well
as from rich clients, you need to
centralize the business logic uh so that
it's not done redundant in all of the
applications.
Okay.
And that's the reason for using
component technology.
Mhm. Okay.
There are those um
and and of course uh the goal was to do
everything in component uh in a
component-oriented system. So, you have
one centralized component-oriented
system that runs on a large cluster. The
mainframe becomes nothing more but uh a
data store, and the centralized business
logic is used throughout whole company.
So, this is sort of what the the vendors
of such component-oriented systems
mentioned as their ultimate goal in
terms of
IT infrastructure.
And you're saying this didn't happen or
that wasn't a good idea or because we we
still go on. We're not yet at SOA, so
there is something that has to change.
Yeah, and I mean, quite obvious if you
look at how the
projects
were done by that time.
So, for example, in in our case,
uh
there is a new fulfillment system
done in our company.
And this fulfillment system is, of
course, done in a component-oriented
matter.
And has interfaces to the call center
and to the order system on the
mainframe.
And is sitting somewhere in the IT
infrastructure.
And now you can use this
um
this fulfillment system from the website
and from the call center, so that works.
But, there is no clear strategy to get
rid of the business logic that is on the
mainframe. I mean, there could be a
strategy that would be to take all the
logic and put it on the
component-oriented system, but that
usually didn't work as you already
mentioned because
it's a lot of business logic.
It's a huge risk because you're changing
the system that the business really
relies on.
And it's also something that has a
rather weak return on investment because
you invest a lot of money to get rid of
the mainframe system, but the return on
what you get back is better
maintainability probably if you do it
right. Which is something that
will just give you a return over several
years because it's easier to develop new
software and this is just a productivity
enhancement and it's not something that
has business value in itself. It just
makes it easier to generate new business
value.
And therefore, what you end up with is
a larger mess than you had before
because you you now have the mainframe
with some parts of the business logic.
You have a separate component-oriented
system with other parts of the business
logic. And
uh the
the front ends talk probably to both of
those systems and you end up with more
systems and there is no clear strategy
or there is no way of getting rid of the
mainframe.
Still
um
still what you get is um better use
because you can have the same front end
for web and rich client applications as
we mentioned.
You mean you have the same back end for
web and rich client applications.
Exactly.
Yeah, you said front end.
Front end. Okay. And there were patterns
and practices established for developing
such component-oriented systems. So, we
know how to do them with those rather
procedural interfaces and object
orientation internally. So, that's
something that we learned there.
So, what it comes down to is that there
is
still the mainframe as sort of
an alien part of the IT infrastructure
uh because you say this is something
that we want to get rid of and there is
a strategy to get rid of it, but the
strategy is not really um useful because
it just doesn't pay off.
Okay.
Okay. And
So, the next step would be
to take a look rather at the IT
infrastructure instead of um doing new
applications. So, what you what you see
picture, basically.
Yeah. So, what you usually see in those
companies is that there is a lot of
several applications. In our case, it's
just component system and some mainframe
system that you did yourself. Usually,
there is also SAP or or other ERP
applications involved.
There is some CRM system and things like
that.
And all of those applications somehow
work together, and there is a large
a large infrastructure in place for the
communication between those
applications.
And this usually leads to heterogeneous
environments,
to redundant data that is somewhere
stored in those systems. And
usually, this is a big problem. So, the
centralized application server that
component-oriented systems we're talking
about by that time is just unrealistic,
and we'd rather have to look into in the
integration domain.
So, instead of trying to change
everything and run everything in one
infrastructure, we're now changing our
focus to how can we integrate those
various infrastructures so that they
form a consistent whole?
Yeah. And
this is
the buzzword for this is obviously
enterprise application integration.
And the idea is to have one centralized
integration infrastructure instead of
having every application to
talk with every other application.
And the reason for that is to is it
rather technical one. So, instead of
dealing with all those
integrations, everybody talks to
everybody else, you can just talk to one
centralized bus.
So, that's where the enterprise
what is it called? Enterprise bus or
integration bus or whatever comes in?
Yeah, exactly.
And
uh
in our company this has been done. So,
they
did centralize bus of some kind
and integrated the call center
application, the fulfillment application
and all these other applications that
were around like CRM systems, ERP
systems and so on.
And
what they learned is that it's rather
focused on data and transformation.
And on the good side there are prepared
adapters for several different systems,
CRM systems, CRM systems and so on. And
of course, the big issue is it's
a distributed system, so you have to
think about performance because the
network is in there and this can
probably
lead to some problems in this field
because of network latency and network
throughput.
So, so one thing that might be worth
mentioning is also that this was also
the phase, I guess, when there was a
change of focus from typically like
remote procedure call oriented
applications as in client server systems
over to message oriented systems where
asynchronous communication based on
well-defined data structures was was was
kind of invented or or or done.
Yeah, in a certain way I think message
oriented systems have been around for
quite some time.
Yeah, yeah, in in the very Yeah, it
wasn't invented there. Um like air
airplane reservation systems and stuff
have always been asynchronous and
message oriented, but in this enterprise
uh
consolidation area, that's I think where
where message oriented became more
important.
Yeah, rather fashionable, I would think,
because
because if you think about distributed
systems in general, I still believe that
most of the that
a rather large part is done with uh, MQ
series, which is called WebSphere MQ,
and this is clearly a a message oriented
system and has been around for ages. So,
Yeah, true.
to a certain It's It's rather about uh,
what becomes fashionable and what people
talk about now in
plus you're right in this field.
In terms of the IT strategy uh, of the
company as a whole, um,
something else is now important. The
mainframe becomes
uh, a partner. It's not something where
you would say, "Okay, this has to go in
in a certain timeframe or it's kind of
old technology and we want don't really
want to use it anymore." So, it's really
taking this into account and not saying
we have to migrate away from it.
And uh, it's also the first time that
there is a strategy in place that takes
the whole company into the picture.
So, it's not saying, "Okay, we have to
somehow migrate this this application."
But, it's rather
It's rather about the whole IT
infrastructure.
Okay.
But, still I mean, um,
talking about enterprise application
integration, there is um,
those projects were also quite big.
Uh, there are several problems. So, for
example, where do you set the priorities
cuz you can't really
have the
um,
the integration system
integrate all of the systems at once.
What
What Which sen- What sense is there in a
partial integration?
And also,
even though technically there is one bus
in place now,
the
every application can still talk to
every other application.
Logically, content-wise.
Yeah, exactly. So, it's becoming even
more easy to have a big mess in terms of
who talks to who.
And this is now about uh dependencies,
and we had an episode about this. So,
dependencies in terms of the whole IT
system.
And uh
it could become even less structured
this way. So, there is some structuring
missing here. It's a rather technical
approach. And uh it's not really talking
about
uh the business logic and how business
logic should talk to each other.
So, this is now, I think, the point
where we uh transition to SOA, right?
Yeah, exactly.
Okay.
So,
So, everything's going to be better with
SOA.
Probably.
Yeah, okay.
If you think about uh what we we've been
talking about so far, we've been talking
about this order process. And actually,
talking about the order process, it's
quite obvious that it's really a
business process. So, what you should
rather think about is what this business
process contains.
So, you could say, "Okay, there is the
CRM, and you have to
somehow say, 'Okay, this customer has
called and has placed an order.'"
You probably have an inventory system,
and you have to uh
to
take a look at the inventory for the
article that is um ordered.
And uh you have a billing system, and
you have to do the invoice in the
billing system and things like that.
So, you would If you think about the
business process as a whole, you would
rather think about uh several steps that
have some business meaning, like um
note that there was uh a contact to this
customer,
put do the billing, and things like
that.
And
Are you saying Are you saying that the
the first shift in mindset for SOA is
actually thinking about business
processes and not about different IT
systems in isolation?
Actually, I think this is
uh
the main step of SOA. So, instead of
saying uh there are those systems and
they talk to each other, it's rather
about uh there is a business process and
the IT has to somehow execute this
business process or support the
execution of the business process
because parts of course are done uh not
automatically but rather by some human
beings out there doing some stuff.
And the interesting part is that this
view of the business process itself is
somehow lost.
Because what you're talking about in the
IT uh structure is there are several um
systems and those systems talk to each
other
uh about data and things like that and
there is no place where the business
process
comes in.
And
uh
you can
if you think about that, so we were
talking about an order process.
Uh if somebody calls in and
um
he he wants to know the actual state of
the order he he has placed uh back then,
it's still that there are some uh
some services, some systems talking to
each other
uh to get the order status. So, you have
the call center application, some
fulfillment, and so on.
But it's probably different systems and
different parts of those systems that
are used. And this is not apparent in
the overall IT infrastructure. You can't
see you you're just talking about
applications and how applications talk
to each other. You're not talking about
how uh the business processes are
executed and which systems take part in
which business process.
So you're saying just to to recap the
important point about SO A is not that
you should define services that are
reusable and stuff but rather that you
should focus on thinking about the
business process, model it explicitly
and then as a consequence
make the building blocks of those
processes reusable in the form of
services because so you can use the
steps in various processes.
And also that you
you have this notion of a business
process in place somewhere in the IT
infrastructure because
Okay.
at the end of the day IT is just about
executing business processes at least
the IT that we usually face which is
business IT.
Yeah.
And it's quite in a way it's quite funny
that even though this is like the real
meaning of IT, it's something that is
just not there in the IT systems. It's
not somewhere explicitly modeled. It's
not something that is really used in
those IT structures and this is pre
I think the thing that SO A wants to
change.
Okay.
Um
Yeah, so business processes are
distributed among those applications
and
in each application business process
just part of this application is used.
So what you already mentioned in a way
is that
instead of talking about applications,
you have to have a different
a thing that
the IT
consists of because it doesn't make
sense to talk about applications if you
want to talk about business processes
because it's not applications that take
place in that take part in the business
process but rather parts of those
applications.
But didn't we have those parts of
applications already? We called them
components in one of those previous
incarnations of enterprise IT.
In a way this is true because if you do
component oriented systems, you usually
have some some services that you export.
But this is just true for component
oriented systems. If you think about a
mainframe system
that has some kind of batch interface in
the file files are transferred to this
system. It's not that apparent anymore.
Although it has been common practice to
build
componentized or service oriented
adapters on top of the mainframe
interfaces.
Yeah.
So so so in some way you're saying
component based architectures plus
explicit business process representation
and modeling, that's basically what what
SOA is all about.
The key point is
that there is
a sort of an
um
there is a reason for using component
oriented systems now and there is a
general um
like the great meaning of life
for component oriented systems or rather
for services at all in the the IT and
this is this business process view.
That's sort of the thing. It's not it's
not really
a technology. It's rather how you think
about IT in general and how you want to
have this IT done.
And if you do component oriented
systems, it's a technical thing that you
have to have
and
a certain way of implementing things.
And with SOA you cannot say, "Okay, I'm
doing this because I want to have
this
fine-grained services that are more
fine-grained than the applications that
we are talking about and I want to have
this because I want to execute business
processes and those business processes
contain of services. So you're not
really doing something different
in terms if you implement a new system,
but you are rather thinking differently
about the IT infrastructure as a whole.
So, instead for example, instead of
saying, "Okay, I'm going to
to
migrate away from the mainframe." You
would rather say, "I will
separate I will
divide this mainframe into several
services
and I will integrate those services into
my business processes.
And if there is some business service
that needs to be changed in a way, I
will have this business service replaced
or done something with it.
And this is different from what you
would do with component-oriented systems
because there the strategy was just to
say, "Sooner or later we are going to
get rid of the mainframe system and
somehow we have to do that probably in a
large project." And here you say, "We
are going to integrate this. We are
going to have services and then we will
see what to do with those services."
Okay. And the other reason for doing
this is
if you usually if you change a business
process
in the company, you would usually come
up with a new system somewhere
and put that in place. So, for example,
if you say the
for the order system, you now have to
have a bonus program so you can earn
points and
get rewarded or get have a sort of
customer ranking that says, "This
customer is more important to us because
we make more revenue with this
customer." And things like that. You
would usually end up with putting a new
system somewhere in place that is
responsible for this business project
and you would somehow change all the
other applications
while thinking about it
the SOA way, you would say, "We need
probably need to
new servers. We need to change the
business process as a rule and we need
to have new services integrated into
this and it can then become more logical
where you put this new functionality in
place and how you integrate these
things. So it's just a different I think
the main thing is that you're thinking
differently about IT and how to deal
with IT.
Uh
while on the technology side it's uh
more or less
the same that we've been doing so far.
So
but but but don't we have to use web
services for everything?
Not at all.
Because
I had to add that.
Yeah, because um
I think uh the relationship between web
services and SOA is that web services
are sort of uh one technology that you
could use to integrate uh several
different uh systems.
And um they're fashionable. That's one
thing.
Yeah.
And they are sort of easy uh to develop
even though this is arguably
Sort of.
Yeah, and also uh
the the I think one advantage is that
it's um
it's more broadly usable. So for
example, doing COBOL in Perl is probably
not the thing that you want to do.
While doing uh a web service call with
some uh it was some XML stuff in Perl is
not that hard. You can actually do that.
So this is sort of the thing.
An integration middleware basically.
Yeah, so so
Right.
It's good for for some parts and not so
good for other.
Yeah. So what are the main steps that I
have to take to to get to an SOA to
service oriented architecture?
So what you need to do is you need to
sort of refactor your existing
applications so that they become um a
set of services.
You need to integrate those services as
parts of business processes to business
processes. And this is where uh
technologies such as BPEL come in to
execute business processes.
You need to generally
BPEL is the business process execution
language, right? It's a a formal
description for business processes and
their steps and orchestration for them.
in the web service technology stack.
Right.
Exactly.
And you need to focus on business
processes
and then integrate those business
processes and make business processes
part of the architecture. And I think
we're going to talk about this in the
following episodes.
Right.
Um and what you gain then is that you
can, for example, easily export those
services to other companies
uh by having some kind of distributed
system across
borders of uh enterprises. And you could
also integrate portal servers to have uh
like a generalized graphic user
interfaces to your SOA. This is
generally, yeah, what SOA is about. And
of course, SOA is it's service oriented
architecture, so it's an architecture,
not a technology as we mentioned. And
talking about architectures, you have to
think about in my opinion, an
architecture is about which parts you
have to use to build up a software
system. In the SOA, this is quite
obvious. It's services. And the
leitmotif for that is to have business
processes in the IT implemented with
services. That's kind of the idea.
And therefore, you cannot easily just
buy an SOA. You have to somehow install
it in your uh
in your IT and it's a means of
restructuring the IT of company.
Right.
That's really important because many of
the of the ESB vendors and of the
middleware vendors are trying to make
you believe that you can basically you
buy some web service web services bus or
some enterprise integration bus and that
makes you a service oriented
architecture. So, that's probably
nonsense.
Yeah, and
while you still you can still say that
um
there needs to be a technical foundation
for an SOA.
And one technical foundation that you
can use is for example an enterprise
application integration system or some
kind of message bus. The idea is that
but the enterprise application
integration system is rather technical
oriented and data oriented. So, SOA puts
sort of a meaning to enterprise
application integration and as we
already mentioned also object
orientation components come into place
with SOA because component oriented
systems are
sort of a way of implementing those
services that we've been talking about.
That's something we're going to talk
about in the next SOA episode SOA
episode more extensively.
And I think you are you are saying that
rather model driven software development
is the way to implement those systems
but we'll see about that.
And also object orientation is still
reason reasonably in those
infrastructures because you can use
object orientation as a means for doing
the analysis and you can also use object
orientation
to implement those services. So, and
this is quite nice. So, with a
enterprise application integration
components and object orientation the
basic technologies are in place and we
know how to deal with those.
So, the new thing is just thinking about
IT structure in terms of or about IT
architecture in a different way. So,
it's not risky in terms of the
technologies that we are using as we
already mentioned. For example, MQ
Series has been around for ages.
It's rather about how to structure the
IT and this is not so risky.
So, but but one thing I think is really
worth mentioning and that is that
as you say it's basically
What you need to do is to is to
restructure the IT landscape of your
whole enterprise at least in the end
goal and that means that you have a lot
of organizational challenges to face,
right?
Exactly and it means that it's actually
something
that needs to be done on the
in terms of the whole IT infrastructure.
It's not something where you could say
we are doing this with this system only.
It's
the full benefit is only
achieved if you do it on the scale of
the whole system.
So, migrating to an SOA is basically a
strategic project. So, it's big and that
makes it highly likely to fail.
Yeah, well, but
what you're saying is you can't do any
projects any large projects at all and
um
Some people actually really say that,
yes.
But now honestly, I mean the the point
is
what I think is really a challenge in
SOA and what I experienced in several
attempts, let's put it this way, is how
to um
implement the transition to SOA in a way
that doesn't require the whole
enterprise to change their mind or the
whole middleware infrastructure to be
changed at at at one time. To to to come
up with a step-by-step process and also
see benefits of that step-by-step
process in rather early phases than only
after 3 years when everything is done. I
think that's really challenge setting up
such a such a transition pragmatically.
Yeah, you're talking about several
different issues here. So, one of the
the technical side, I mean, it's still
challenging.
But, the question is whether you really
need to have one infrastructure in place
and because you could also have multiple
infrastructures that somehow integrate
to have this conceptual bus. So, you
could say, "Okay, one part is done with
some message-oriented system for those
mainframes and there is another part
that is done with the JMS for the Java
systems and those somehow integrate and
things like that." And the other thing
that you've been talking about is that
you actually need to need to change the
mind of the whole IT. And this is
completely true.
I mean, that's what we are talking
about, a general shift. And therefore,
you need to change the whole
idea about how IT is done. And this is
probably This is a big challenge, of
course.
Yeah.
But, this is a big challenge in terms of
organizational stuff.
Absolutely.
And I mean, if you want to change how IT
works in your company, it's quite an
issue anyway. So.
Yeah.
If you have an SOA
architecture in place,
it's usually associated with
flexibility. So, you can easily change
your business processes now.
And actually, I think this is only part
of the truth because what you can do now
if you have those services in place, you
can say
there are certain services that needs to
be flexible.
So,
I can I keep them in-house. I develop
them in-house because then I can easily
change those services
and
can have my special requirements done in
those services.
And I could also,
uh, change the business process in my,
uh, SOA architecture more easily.
Um, so that's one thing that you can
gain flexibility for certain services if
you want them to be flexible. There are
other services that you don't need to be
so flexible.
Uh, and in those services you can use
economy of scale. So you could say,
"Okay, this is something that everybody
more or less does in the same way."
And you can then
either choose to have this service
offered to other companies or have your
own implementation replaced by services
that are offered by other companies.
So what you're saying is because you
modularize your application business
logic into well-defined services, you
can decide for each of them whether you
want to go to, uh, do it yourself
because it's mission critical and and
you know, it's a it's a in a unique
selling point kind of thing, or whether
you want to, you know, like like like
bookkeeping, something you just, uh,
outsource and use some standard process.
Yeah.
Or some standard service.
Or standard software. And the interest,
I mean, this sounds like far out future
stuff,
but actually this is already happening.
So for example, in Germany, there is one
bank that is doing, uh, the transfers
between accounts for most of the larger
banks.
Uh, and this is ex- actually exactly
what I'm talking about. This bank can
use economy of scale, so they can offer
it more cheaply than the individual
banks can actually do it
because they have a larger volume.
And the other banks say, "Okay, um, this
is not something that we want to be
flexible, uh, about because it's like
normal stuff." And
Bread and butter stuff.
Yeah, exactly. And for that reason, it's
already in place. The other thing that
you can do is you can have rather um
economy of scope, so you can say, "I'm
going to have a better quality in this
specific scope. I'm going to be more
specialized in this one sector that I'm
talking about." And you are doing the
same thing then. You can either choose
to export your services say, "Everybody
else might use it because I'm doing it
in the best way." Or you could uh
integrate services of other vendors. One
example that is quite common is customer
rating. So, companies that make a living
out of uh offering ratings for customers
uh
because they know how their financial
status is or they know where the
customer lives and they therefore they
have uh an estimate about how uh
how much money the customer has and
things like that.
So,
this is uh So, what you end up with is
that you separate your IT into those
services.
And then you can talk uh think about
those services and say, "Okay,
uh if those are things that we want to
be flexible about because it's our
unique selling proposition, we're going
to keep it in-house and have it more
easily changed. If you want to have uh
less
costs or a better quality, you can
outsource it to some other people
because of economy of scope or economy
of scale. And uh you could or you could
replace it with standard software. And
what you end up with is a marketplace of
services that um
and each company uses a part of those
services, some of them in-house, some of
them somewhere else. And as I mentioned,
I think this is already taking place.
The business demands are there. We we
have two
uh examples that are quite common
already.
And therefore, SOA is probably
inevitable. Something that has to take
place because those things are already
happening.
Mhm.
Of course, being cynic and skeptic, one
could always say that back then in the
component days, people talked about
component marketplaces that people could
buy or they actually could buy the
components and run them in their own
computing centers. So, the difference
now is you don't buy the components and
run it yourself. You actually just kind
of connect to a service that somebody
else provides and reuse that one.
Yeah. And also, it's it's important to
point out that
um
I'm not talking about the UDDI stuff
here. UDDI is this universal discovery
uh directory and discovery
interface infrastructure. I don't know.
Uh and this it So, this uh
should be a registry that is worldwide
and everybody can somehow offer services
and other people can use those services.
And this
didn't really take off. And I believe
um the reason for that is because uh
it's too anonymous. So, what I'm talking
about here is that on the probably even
on the level of the executive board, one
company talks to another and says, "I'm
going to outsource my whatever to you."
And then this has to be somehow done in
IT. And this is not something about
automatic discovery of services and
things like that. It's rather
about uh
a strategic issue of the whole company.
And for that reason,
uh it's different from the UDDI approach
that was in place originally with web
services and so on.
Right.
Okay.
That's it, isn't it?
Yeah. So, um thanks a lot for listening.
And uh the subsequent episodes in SOA
will, as we mentioned already, take a
look at some more technical uh issues,
like for example, some new technologies
that come up. We'll also take a look at
web services and some of the standards
there. Um we'll take a look at
model-driven development and SOA, how
they fit together. And finally, we'll
have uh another
uh episode which looks a bit more
skeptical on SOA and and talks about the
challenges uh organizationally and and
also in in actually implementing an SOA
in in in a large uh enterprise.
Yeah, so if this was too high-level and
too far out for you, uh then you could
listen to those episode. And of course,
we would be happy about any feedback
that you could would give us.
Okay, so before we close this session, I
want to mention that Wiley has reopened
the special offer for getting the book
on model-driven software development. Um
you might remember we had this promo
call code called FAD.
And uh they have reopened it until the
end of October, I think. So, if you're
interested in getting the model-driven
software development book we talked
about in previous episodes, you can go
to the Wiley website and get the book I
think 20% off the regular price.
Okay, so thanks for listening. See you
next time. Bye.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. If you want to get
more information about Software
Engineering Radio or if you want to give
us feedback, please go to our website at
SE-Radio.net.
You can also contact the team at
team@se-radio.net.
Although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think. Software
Engineering Radio wants to thank Henning
Pauli for the intro and outro music as
well as LiipSync for providing the
bandwidth.
This episode of SE-Radio as well as all
other episodes is licensed under
Creative Commons License. See the
Software Engineering Radio website for
details.